<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to two books the first being stiled a reply to Sir Thomas Mainwaring's book, entituled, An answer to Sir Peter Leicester's Addenda, the other stiled Sir Thomas Mainwaring's law-cases mistaken / written ... Sir T.M.</title>
            <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21694</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12618224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12618224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64437</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64437)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 673:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to two books the first being stiled a reply to Sir Thomas Mainwaring's book, entituled, An answer to Sir Peter Leicester's Addenda, the other stiled Sir Thomas Mainwaring's law-cases mistaken / written ... Sir T.M.</title>
                  <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Leicester's Addenda is the addition to his Historical antiquities.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Historical antiquities.</term>
               <term>Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64437:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Two Books: The firſt being ſtiled A REPLY TO Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi>'s Book, ENTITULED, AN ANSWER TO Sir <hi>Peter Leiceſter</hi>'s Addenda; The other ſtiled Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi>'s LAW-CASES MISTAKEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the ſaid Sir</hi> T. M.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam: Lowndes,</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter</hi> Houſe in the <hi>Strand.</hi> M.DC.I.XXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64437:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64437:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               </seg>Pon Saturday the <hi>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>December</hi> laſt, I received from Sir <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Leyceſter</hi> a Book, or Books, thus called, <hi>viz.</hi> Two Books: The first being ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, A Reply to Sir <hi>Thomas Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi>'s Book, Entituled, An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Sir <hi>Peter Leyceſter</hi>'s <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda;</hi> The other ſtiled, Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mainwaring</hi>'s Law-caſes Miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: And although the one of theſe was dated the <hi>14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day of <hi>April 1674.</hi> And the other the first day of <hi>May</hi> following; yet, they came not out in Print till <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term in the ſame year. When I had peruſed the ſaid Books, I found the
<pb facs="tcp:64437:3"/>latter, to be the ſame in effect with the former, and ſcarce met with any thing in either, which he had not had in ſome of his Books before, and had been formerly anſwered; ſo that it was much more difficult to find out any new Matter, than to give an Anſwer to the ſame.</p>
            <p>I believe the Reader (when he remembers how Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> did declare, <hi>That he had taken leave for ever of this Trivial Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi>) will very much wonder to find him in Print, twice ſince then, upon the ſame Subject; But for that, he ſuppoſeth he hath a good Excuſe: For he tells us in his Epiſtle to the Reader, before the firſt of his two Books, That <hi>although his reſolution then was (viz.</hi> when he writ his Anſwer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia, 1673.) to have writ no more about
<pb facs="tcp:64437:3"/>it, (eſpecially if I had let him alone;) yet now, contrary to his former intention, he is neceſſitated thereunto in his own defence, for the removal of thoſe unjuſt oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies which are ſince caſt upon him;</hi> Whereas his Servant Mr. <hi>Thomas Jackſon,</hi> in a Letter, (writen, as he ſays, by the Command of his Maſter) did ſignifie to me, that his Maſter would write again, and this, before I had printed one word of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: ſo that if we find him thus ſtumbling at the firſt, it is well, if we do not take him oft tripping, before he comes to his journies end. And for his writing again this ſecond time, he hath an excellent Reaſon; For he ſays, pag. <hi>16. I have publiſhed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Book ſince, and have (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) taxed him already for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt to his word; ſo that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now incur a greater Cenſure
<pb facs="tcp:64437:4"/>from me herein, though he alter his former reſolution and intention, and write in his own defence, ſo long as he ſhall henceforth judge it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> ſo that he is reſolved to give me juſt cauſe to cenſure him, if he had not done ſo before. He alſo endeavors to apply to me that ſaying of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Man in the Comedy, which he mentions in his ſaid <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> but yet he is conſcious I will ſay as much of him, and his <hi>Reply,</hi> and thereupon ſubmits it to the Reader; in which I ſhall willingly cloſe with him, and eſpecially if it be a Reader who is well acquainted with his temper and mine: But it is high time to leave the <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and to proceed to give an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his ſaid Books.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64437:4"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO Sir <hi>Peter Leyceſter</hi>'s TWO BOOKS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not but the Judicious Reader hath long ſince obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what ſtrange kind of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments Sir <hi>Peter Leyceſter</hi> doth inſiſt upon, both in theſe laſt, and in all other his former Books; For with all the confidence imaginable he ſeveral times affirms, that Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> ſays, That Lands might be given with any Woman <hi>in Liberum Maritagium:</hi> whereas he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſays, That they may be given <hi>cum qualibet muliere in Maritagium,</hi> as you may ſee in the 39, 40, and 41 pages of my Reply, where Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s words are expreſly ſet down.</p>
            <p>He alſo ſays, That he hath proved <hi>Geva</hi> to be a Baſtard, out of an Hiſtorian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64437:5"/>Contemporary, by which <hi>Ordericus Vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> is meant, and yet the ſaid <hi>Ordericus</hi> hath ſaid no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>He alſo affirms, That the Common Law is now alter'd other ways than by Act of Parliament, without quoting any Author for what he ſays, although the Common Law hath always been the ſame, and as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, fol.</hi> 115. <hi>b.</hi> ſays, Hath no Controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in any part of it, but the High Court of Parliament; and if it be not abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated or alter'd by Parliament, it remains ſtill. And whereas my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> doth alſo in the ſame Book, <hi>fol</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> tell us, That theſe words, <hi>in liberum maritagium,</hi> are ſuch words of Art, and ſo neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required, as they cannot be expreſſed by words equipollent, or amounting to as much; He, for all this, brags of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Precedents where Lands were given in free Marriage with Baſtards, and yet proves not that thoſe neceſſary words <hi>in Liberum Maritagium,</hi> were uſed in the granting of any of thoſe Lands, or that any of thoſe perſons with whom the ſaid Lands were given were Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64437:5"/>
            <p>To conclude, he tells you, That <hi>Lhewellin</hi> Prince of <hi>North-Wales,</hi> was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from his Wife <hi>Joane</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>John;</hi> and for this he can neither ſhew any Author or Record, but only doth dream of ſuch a thing himſelf: and yet you muſt believe him in all theſe particulars, or elſe (as you may ſee in the firſt page of his <hi>Reply</hi> to my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda</hi>) he will tell you, you do withſtand the plaineſt truth of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> produced.</p>
            <p>He alſo hath a fine way of <hi>anſwering;</hi> For if he be preſſed overmuch with any point of Law, he will tell you, <hi>of his own authority,</hi> that the Law in ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars hath been clearly alter'd, though he cannot tell how, or at what time it was ſo changed. If it be a Record that puts him too hard to it, then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the <hi>Roll</hi> from whence the Deed is written, is miſtaken in ſuch and ſuch words, and <hi>miſwrit therein from the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Chart it ſelf.</hi> And if out of any Hiſtory, you tell him of any thing which he cannot anſwer, then he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the words to be read as they ought to be printed; but he will fancy ſuch expreſſions as will beſt ſuit with his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64437:6"/>turn: and will alſo diſparage the ſaid Hiſtory, although in thoſe matters he had formerly ſaid he did chiefly follow the ſame.</p>
            <p>He doth alſo, to amuſe thoſe Readers that are of weak underſtanding, tell them of <hi>Circumquaques,</hi> of <hi>bits of Law, pieces of Law,</hi> brought in by the head and ſhoulders, <hi>fragments</hi> of Law, <hi>parcels</hi> of Law; and in his two laſt Books, tells me of my <hi>impertinencies,</hi> of my being <hi>impertinent,</hi> and of my ſpeaking <hi>imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently,</hi> (if one who ſayes he hath counted, do not miſtake himſelf) no leſs than Thirty times; with ſeveral other expreſſions, too ridiculous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat here.</p>
            <p>He alſo, to keep up his credit with the more ſimple ſort of People, doth offer to <hi>join iſſue with me</hi> upon very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Points; and gives me ſome ſtrange directions to follow: which done, <hi>he will then leave it to the World to judge, otherwiſe there will never be an end.</hi> Whereas I will refer it to all judicious perſons, whether his Arguments in theſe two Books, be not the ſame which he uſed formerly? and whether they be not ſufficiently anſwered by me in my other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64437:6"/>Books? which if ſo, the Controverſie is already at an end.</p>
            <p>Now for the manifeſtation of what I have here alledged, I ſhall deſire the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader, when Sir <hi>Peter Leyceſter</hi> ſpeaks of what Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> hath ſaid, to take notice what is written in the 32 page of my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia,</hi> and ſo on to the 43 page; as alſo what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the 39, 40, and 41 pages of my <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he ſays <hi>Geva</hi> is a Baſtard, then I deſire the Reader to peruſe the 43, 44, and 45 pages of my ſaid <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> and the 45, 46, 47, and 48 pages of my <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he ſays that the Gift to <hi>Geva</hi> was a Gift in <hi>frank marriage,</hi> or that the Town of <hi>Drayton Baſſet</hi> did paſs to the Heirs of <hi>Geva</hi> by vertue of that Deed which <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> made to her; ſee my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia,</hi> pag. 48, 49, and 50; and the 55, 56, 57, 58, and 59 pages of my <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he ſays that <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> which King <hi>John</hi> had by <hi>Agatha,</hi> then read the 3, 4, and 5 pages of my Anſwer to his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64437:7"/>
            <p>When he ſays, that <hi>Elleſmere</hi> was given with the ſaid <hi>Joane in Libero Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio;</hi> ſee the 6 and 7 pages of my ſaid Book.</p>
            <p>When he ſays, King <hi>John</hi> had not three Daughters called <hi>Joane,</hi> or that <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> who was Wife to <hi>Robert de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deley;</hi> Read the 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 22, 23, and 24 pages of the ſaid <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he ſays, the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from her Husband <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> (which no man ever ſaid but he himſelf) then read the 17, 18, 19, and 20 pages of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> where (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other proofs againſt what he ſays) you will find that the Aduſtery of <hi>Joane,</hi> whil'ſt ſhe was Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was committed <hi>Anno Domini ſequenti</hi> to that <hi>Marriage,</hi> which he fancies to be the Marriage of the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> Wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Robert de Audeley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he ſays, <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was a Baſtard; then ſee the 21, and ſo on to the end of the 30 page of the ſaid Book. And although he ſays, page 50. that what I ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64437:7"/>King <hi>John</hi>'s legitimate Daughter by his Wife <hi>Hawiſe,</hi> is ſo ridiculous, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other would be aſham'd to own it: Yet I can ſhew under the hands of perſons eminently knowing in theſe matters, what great ſatisfaction they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in this particular, by what I have written concerning the ſame; alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe proofs which I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought, he doth acknowledge that <hi>Vaughan</hi> in his <hi>Britiſh Antiquities,</hi> pag. 29. doth call her the <hi>Daughter</hi> of King <hi>John:</hi> and in a Record concerning <hi>Budiford,</hi> mention'd by me hereafter in this Book, ſhe is alſo called the <hi>Siſter</hi> of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> III, without the leaſt blemiſh of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardy at all.</p>
            <p>I might here very well make an end, but becauſe ſome perſons may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with ſome of Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Flouriſhes, I ſhall (paſſing by his angry and uncivil Language, with which he doth ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound) endeavor to clear ſome things, by which he might otherways impoſe upon ſome ſilly men.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of his two Books in his ſecond page, he ſays, I had in the 55 pag. of my <hi>Reply</hi> to his <hi>Anſwer,</hi> ſaid, thoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64437:8"/>Reaſons of mine (there mentioned) were unanſwerable; whereas I ſaid, <hi>they were not at all anſwered by him; and that the one of them was ſo far from being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that it was not underſtood by him, unleſs he only pretended not to underſtand it, becauſe he perceived he could not give an anſwer to it;</hi> ſo that it ſeems, in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to doubt whether he can anſwer an Argument, is the ſame thing as to ſay, it is unanſwerable.</p>
            <p>In his fourth and fifth pages, he won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders if I can engliſh the words <hi>in Libero Conjugio,</hi> that I will not allow ſuch a Gift to be a Gift <hi>in Frank Marriage;</hi> and yet he doth acknowledge, that a Gift in <hi>Connubio ſoluto ab omni ſervitio,</hi> is not a Gift <hi>in Free Marriage:</hi> whereas if conſtruing might be the Rule in this Caſe, that might be made a Gift <hi>in Free Marriage</hi> as well as the other; for the word <hi>Connubium,</hi> as you may ſee in <hi>Gouldman</hi>'s <hi>Dictionary,</hi> doth only ſignifie <hi>Lawful Wedlock</hi> or <hi>Marriage;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a better word than his word <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugium,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> as well as <hi>Lawful Conjunction:</hi> If conſtruing might alſo take place in this Caſe, a Gift <hi>in Libero Conjugio,</hi> or a Gift <hi>in Libero
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64437:8"/>Connubio,</hi> would be a Gift in <hi>Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> at this day, as well as formerly, and all other equipollent words would alſo amount unto ſuch Gifts; whereas the Law, for the reaſon given by my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> will, in this Caſe, allow of no ſuch Gift, unleſs there be uſed both the word <hi>Liberum,</hi> and the word <hi>Maritagium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He alſo in the ſaid fourth page, doth again miſrecite that Argument of mine, which he doth there mention; for he ſays, that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, that theſe words <hi>in Liberum Maritagium,</hi> are ſuch words of Art, and ſo neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as they cannot be <hi>underſtood</hi> by words equipollent; whereas my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſays, <hi>they cannot be</hi> expreſſed <hi>by words equipollent, or amounting to as much;</hi> ſo hard it is to get Sir <hi>Peter</hi> either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, or underſtand aright.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventh page he alſo miſtakes himſelf very much, when he tells you, that Lands given <hi>in Maritagium, Haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſibi &amp; Haeredibus ſuis libere &amp; quiete ab omni ſervitio verſus Capitalem Dominum de me &amp; Haeredibus meis,</hi> was a good Grant <hi>in Free Marriage,</hi> by the very words of <hi>Glanvil</hi> in thoſe ancient Ages, and was as good as <hi>in Liberum Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64437:9"/>if he means thereby, that Lands might be given <hi>in Free Marriage,</hi> by thoſe words of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> in a Deed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out uſing the words <hi>in Liberum Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium;</hi> for Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> doth there only tell us what <hi>Free Marriage</hi> is, and it is the ſame now that it was then; but Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> doth not there, or any where elſe ſay, that Lands may be given <hi>in Free Marriage</hi> by thoſe, or any other equipollent words, without uſing the words <hi>in Liberum Maritagium;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he ſays this, he ſays nothing for Sit <hi>Peter</hi>'s purpoſe: And this may give an Anſwer to what he hath alſo ſaid in his 14 and 54 pages of his firſt Book, and in the 26 and 27 pages of the latter of his two Books.</p>
            <p>And whereas he doth often tell you in all his Books, that Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> ſays, that Lands may be given with any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>in Liberum Maritagium;</hi> he as often tells you, that which Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> never ſaid. Indeed Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> ſays, that Lands may be given <hi>cum qualibet Muliere,</hi> (with any Woman whatſoever) <hi>in Maritagium;</hi> but when he ſpeaks of Gifts <hi>in Free Marriage,</hi> he ſays, they may be given <hi>cum aliqua Muliere,</hi> (with ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64437:9"/>Woman) and the Law, in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, is ſtill the ſame; for Lands may now be given <hi>in Maritagium,</hi> with any Woman whatſoever; but Lands can only be given <hi>in Free Marriage</hi> with ſome Women, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are of the Kindred of him who gives the Lands.</p>
            <p>He alſo very much miſtakes (and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I doubt) the Deed made in the time of King <hi>John,</hi> where he ſays, <hi>Saher de Quency</hi> Earl of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> granted to <hi>Robert</hi> his Son and Heir, certain Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors <hi>ad dandum in Liberum Dotarium</hi> Hawiſiae <hi>Sorori Comitis</hi> Ceſtriae, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori ejuſdem</hi> Roberti, which Deed I ſhall here give you at large, as I find it in the 133 page of his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>SAherus de Quency</hi> Comes <hi>Wintoniae,</hi> omnibus Hominibus, &amp; Amicis ſuis, praeſentibus &amp; futuris, ſalutem. Sciatis, me conceſſiſſe &amp; dediſſe &amp; praeſenti Chartâ meá confirmaſſe <hi>Roberto de Quency</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio meo &amp; Haeredi ad dandum in liberum Donarium <hi>Hawiſiae</hi> Sorori Comitis <hi>Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori ejuſdem <hi>Roberti, Bucehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiam,</hi> &amp; <hi>Granteſſet,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bradeham,</hi> &amp; <hi>Herdewich,</hi> cum omnibus earundem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum pertinentiis, pro centum Libratis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64437:10"/>terrae: Et ſi hae praedictae terrae non valeans per Annum centum Libras, Ego in aliis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris meis de propriâ Haereditate meâ in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia,</hi> ei tantum perficiam, quòd plenari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habeat centum Libratas terrae per viſum &amp; conſiderationem legalium Militum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num videlicet, Comitis <hi>Ceſtriae,</hi> &amp; meo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Et praeterea Dedi eidem <hi>Roberto</hi> Feoda duorum Militum, ſcilicet, Feo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <hi>Matthei Turpin</hi> in <hi>Winterſlawa</hi> it <hi>Wilteſhire,</hi> pro ſervitio Feodi unius Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ad dandum ſimul cùm terris nominati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praedictae <hi>Hawiſiae</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori ſuae in liberus Donarium. Teſtibus his, Comite <hi>Davide, Willielmo</hi> Comite de <hi>Ferrars, Philippo de Orreby, Roberto de Baſingham, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardo de Lindeſcia, Willielmo de Grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pington, Henrico de Braibroc, Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Syelford, David Giffard, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmo Picot, Hugone</hi> &amp; <hi>Thoma</hi> &amp; <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico Diſpenſariis, Waltero de Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Waltero Daivilla,</hi> &amp; multis aliis.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now as you may ſee in the 29 page of his ſecond Book, he ſays, That in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> the word <hi>Donarium</hi> was there miſprinted for the word <hi>Dotarium;</hi> whereas the word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarium</hi> is not in the ſaid Copy which he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64437:10"/>Cites, as a knowing Friend of mine doth inform me, who, at my requeſt, did very lately and carefully examine the ſame in one of the <hi>Couchir Books</hi> in the <hi>Dutchy Office</hi> in <hi>Grayes-Inn;</hi> but the word is <hi>Donarium,</hi> which probably the Tranſcriber did miſtake for <hi>Douarium,</hi> the <hi>u</hi> and <hi>n</hi> being anciently written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and the <hi>v</hi> conſonant not then uſed. But if the word had been <hi>Dotarium,</hi> it would not ſignifie <hi>Marriage,</hi> as he doth fancy, although <hi>Dos</hi> is <hi>Domeſday Book</hi> be called <hi>Maritagium;</hi> for <hi>Dos</hi> is twofold, and that <hi>Dos</hi> which is <hi>Dotarium,</hi> is the ſame with. <hi>Douarium,</hi> which we in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh call <hi>Dower,</hi> and is not that <hi>Dos</hi> which ſometimes is called <hi>Maritagium:</hi> For this ſee <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 6. cap. 1. whoſe words are theſe, <hi>Dos duobus modis dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, dos enim dicitur vulgaritèr,</hi> id quod aliquis liber homo dat ſponſae ſuae ad oſtium Eccleſiae tempore deſponſationis ſuae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And lib. 7. cap. 1. <hi>In alia enim acceptione, accipiter dos</hi> ſecundum leges Romanas (which three laſt words, with ſome others, he leaves out in the eighth page of the firſt of his two laſt Books) <hi>ſecundum quas proprie appellatur dos, id quod cum muliere datur viro, quod
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64437:11"/>vulgariter dieitur Maritagium;</hi> Now that <hi>Dotarium,</hi> is that <hi>Dos</hi> which is <hi>Dower,</hi> and not that <hi>Dos</hi> which is called <hi>Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> you may ſee in Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi>'s <hi>Gloſſary</hi> Printed at <hi>London</hi> 1664. p. 174. whoſe words are theſe:
<q>¶ De eo Dotis genere, quod uxori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſtituunt Angli.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Doarium, Dodarium, Dotarium, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narium, Dotalitium.]</hi> Omnia recte inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatur vernaculum noſtrum <hi>Douer,</hi> non Latinum dos. Eſt enim propriè <hi>dos,</hi> illud quod maritus accipit cum uxore: haec verò id quod in remunerationen dotis, reportat uxor. And Sir <hi>Peter</hi> very well knows, that what is given in the aforeſaid Deed, was only given as a <hi>Dower</hi> or <hi>Joynture,</hi> and not as a Gift in Free <hi>Marriage,</hi> as you may ſee in the 132 page of his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> where he thus writes:
<q>
                  <hi>HAwiſe,</hi> fourth Daughter of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> by <hi>Bertred,</hi> married <hi>Robert Quency</hi> Son and Heir of <hi>Saher</hi> de <hi>Quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> Earl of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> She had the Earldom of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> to wit, the Caſtle and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64437:11"/>Honour of <hi>Bolingbroke,</hi> and all the Lands of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> in <hi>Lindſey</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> for which ſhe gave <hi>50 <abbr>l.</abbr>
                  </hi> for relief. On <hi>Hawiſe</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>Joynture, Bukby, Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſet, Bradeham,</hi> and <hi>Herdwick,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this Deed in the <hi>Couchir</hi> Book of the <hi>Dutchy Office,</hi> Tom. <hi>2. Honor</hi> ſive <hi>Soca</hi> de Bolingbroke, <hi>num. 26. pag. 508.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After which, he immediately doth <hi>verbatim</hi> recite the aforeſaid Deed; let the Reader therefore judge of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> who in his new Books pretends, that the aforeſaid Lands were given <hi>in Free Marriage</hi> to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Hawiſe;</hi> and yet in his <hi>Hiſtorical An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities,</hi> doth acknowledge that they were eſtated for <hi>Joynture</hi> only, as by his words before mentioned doth clearly appear.</p>
            <p>And whereas he ſays, pag. 9. that it is not abſolutely true which my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> doth ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>at this day, the words</hi> in Liberum Maritagium, <hi>have no other words equipollent; for then a Deed in Engliſh granting Lands</hi> in Free Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, <hi>or a Deed in French de terres</hi> en Frank Marriage <hi>would be void grants; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64437:12"/>of theſe have in ſtrict terms the words</hi> in Liberum Maritagium, <hi>&amp;c. wherefore certainly he underſtood it of a Grant in Latine:</hi> His arguing therein is very weak; for the Engliſh words <hi>in Free Marriage,</hi> and the French words <hi>en Frank Marriage,</hi> are the ſame words in Law, with the Latin words <hi>in Liberum Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium,</hi> though in different Languages; but the words <hi>in Libero Conjugio,</hi> though capable of the ſame conſtruction in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh with the words <hi>in Libero Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> are but equipollent to them, and ſo the words, <hi>in Wedlock free from all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,</hi> are but equipollent to the Engliſh words <hi>in Free Marriage;</hi> and the French words, <hi>en Nopſage acquite de Services,</hi> are but equipollent to the French words, <hi>En Frank Marriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo by this Rule, a gift of Lands, by a Latin Deed <hi>in Libero Maritagio,</hi> would be void, becauſe they are not in ſtrict terms the words <hi>in Liberum Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> ſo that the Reader may ſee what ſtrange kind of Arguments Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth uſe.</p>
            <p>In the 17 page, he tells me, that in the fourth and fifth pages of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda, I further prove, by comparing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64437:12"/>the age of</hi> Bertred, <hi>that</hi> Agatha <hi>could not be Daughter to the ſecond</hi> William de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars <hi>by</hi> Agnes <hi>his Wife;</hi> whereas he is pitifully miſtaken, for I did go about no ſuch thing, but did in the 3, 4, and 5 pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhew, that <hi>Joane,</hi> who was the wife of <hi>Lhewellyn,</hi> could not be the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> which King <hi>John</hi> had by the ſaid <hi>Agatha,</hi> and that was all which I did there prove.</p>
            <p>In the 18 and 19 pages he ſays, that though the Writ (meaning King <hi>John</hi>'s Precept to the Sheriff of <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> to make Livery of <hi>Elleſmere</hi> to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> after his Marriage with <hi>Joane</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>John</hi>) if you begin the year of our Lord the 25th day of <hi>March,</hi> was in the year 1204. yet it would fall out to be in the year 1205, if with ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians we begin the year on the firſt day of <hi>January;</hi> but it would be a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Trick, if from either of theſe reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings, he could make out what he ſaid in the ſecond page of his <hi>Addenda, viz.</hi> that the Marriage of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Joane,</hi> was in the year 1206.</p>
            <p>In his 20 and 21 pages, he thinks he gives me no quarter; for he tells me,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64437:13"/>that <hi>I would diſtinguiſh between</hi> Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, <hi>and</hi> liberum maritagium, <hi>and ſay,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium <hi>is twofold, but I do not give the members of my diſtinction aright; for a good Logician</hi> (Sir <hi>Peter</hi> is the man meant without all doubt) <hi>would tell me, that the members of a good diſtinction muſt be oppoſite, and not as I diſtinguiſh,</hi> Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt duplex, vel maritagium, vel libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum maritagium; <hi>The members are here coincident, for</hi> Liberum maritagium eſt maritagium: Glanvils <hi>diſtinction is good,</hi> Maritagium eſt vel liberum vel ſervitio obnoxium: <hi>ſo that</hi> Maritagium <hi>the</hi> genus <hi>comprehends the members, and both oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite one to another, as either free marriage, or not free marriage.</hi> This is Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s charge, and a very great one, as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves: But for anſwer hereunto, I doubt not but the Reader hath taken notice how in my <hi>Reply,</hi> p. 39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 40. I did obſerve that <hi>Maritagium</hi> was twofold, and that it was diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium liberum,</hi> and <hi>Maritagium ſervitio obnoxium:</hi> ſo that when I did intend to take notice how it was diſtinguiſhed, Sir <hi>Peter</hi> cannot but acknowledge that I did right; the only colour of Cavil that he hath, is, becauſe I afterwards ſay, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64437:13"/>whenſoever any Lands are given in a Deed <hi>in maritagio</hi> only, it is always the ſame thing in Law, as if they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>in maritagium ſervitio obnoxium,</hi> and it is only his want of underſtanding that cauſeth him to blame me for what I ſo ſay, for that expreſſion will not thwart with what I ſaid before; this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, becauſe that <hi>maritagium ſervitio obnoxium,</hi> is the elder Brother to <hi>mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium liberum;</hi> for when Lands are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>in maritagio ſervitio obnoxio,</hi> ſuch Gifts are agreeable to the Common Law of <hi>England;</hi> but when they are given <hi>in liberum maritagium,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. they <hi>create an eſtate of inheritance against the general Rule of the Law;</hi> and therefore though this younger Son be connived at, and tollerated, yet, as you may there ſee, <hi>the Law requireth</hi> that ſuch Gifts be <hi>legally purſued,</hi> and that is the reaſon why ſuch Gifts cannot be made to any but to thoſe of the Blood, as alſo why the words <hi>in liberum maritagium,</hi> are ſuch words of Art, and ſo neceſſarily required, as that they cannot be expreſſed by words equipollent, or amounting to as much: Now the Common Lawyers (as you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64437:14"/>may ſee <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 189. a.) have a Rule, that <hi>Additio probat minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem;</hi> and thereupon it is that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> there tells you, that the younger Son giveth the difference; and purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to this Rule, when a Gift is made <hi>in maritagio,</hi> which is intended to be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſervices, (that being the elder Brother) they uſe the word <hi>maritagio</hi> in the Deed, and no more; but when it is given <hi>in free Marriage,</hi> (which is the younger Brother) according as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> tells you, the word <hi>liberum</hi> (which is the difference) is abſolutely neceſſary: And herewith agrees the common practice; for I never ſaw in all my life, where Lands were given <hi>in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio,</hi> liable to ſervices, that the words <hi>in maritagio ſervitio obnoxio,</hi> were uſed in any of the ſaid Deeds, but only the words <hi>in maritagio;</hi> and if they did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that any other ſervices ſhould be done, over and above thoſe ſervices which the Law did create by the words <hi>in maritagio,</hi> then they did afterwards in the ſaid Deeds, mention thoſe other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, but elſe not.</p>
            <p>Alſo the word <hi>Foedum,</hi> or <hi>Fee,</hi> is two-fold, <hi>viz. Foedum ſimplex,</hi> and <hi>Foedum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64437:14"/>tale,</hi> and yet in this Caſe, like unto the other, <hi>Fee-ſimple</hi> being the elder Brother to <hi>Fee-tayle,</hi> (all Inheritances being in <hi>Fee-ſimple</hi> before the Statute of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> 2. cap. 1. as <hi>Littleton</hi> tells you, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 13.) if it be ſaid in any Book, that a Man is ſeized in <hi>Fee,</hi> without more ſaying, it ſhall be intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Fee-ſimple;</hi> for it ſhall not be intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this word <hi>(in Fee)</hi> that a man is ſeized in <hi>Fee-tayle,</hi> unleſs there be added to it this addition <hi>Fee-tayle,</hi> as you may ſee in <hi>Littleton,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 4. ſect. 293. And according to this Rule, our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers do all of them conſtantly uſe the like expreſſions at this day; ſo that there is no more reaſon for him to tell me, that I do not diſtinguiſh aright in this Caſe of <hi>Maritagium,</hi> than there is to tell them, that they do not diſtinguiſh aright as to the word <hi>Foedum,</hi> the word <hi>Foedum</hi> being as much the <hi>Genus</hi> to <hi>Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple</hi> and <hi>Fee-tayle,</hi> as the word <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> is the <hi>Genus</hi> to <hi>Marriage liable to ſervices,</hi> and to <hi>Frank Marriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But would any one think, if I had committed ſo great an Error herein, (as he would perſuade the World I had done) that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, within a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64437:15"/>very few lines, and in the ſame 21 page, ſhould really be guilty of the like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which he did unjuſtly charge me withall; and yet you ſhall ſee that it is ſo, for both in his 21 page, and 55 page, he tells you, that <hi>Maritagio</hi> was often in thoſe Ages, (<hi>viz.</hi> of Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi>) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood for <hi>libero maritagio,</hi> both by Hiſtorians and old Deeds; you ſhall therefore ſee how Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his 20 and 21 pages, may, <hi>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis mutandis,</hi> be thus retorted upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Here Sir <hi>Peter</hi> would diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>Maritagium,</hi> and <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium ſervitio obnoxium,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> is <hi>twofold,</hi> but doth not give the Members of his Diſtinction aright; for a good Logician would tell Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Members of a good Diſtinction muſt be oppoſite, and not as he doth here diſtinguiſh, <hi>Maritagium eſt duplex, vel maritagium, vel maritagium ſervitio ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxium;</hi> the Members are here coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, for <hi>Maritagium ſervitio obnoxium eſt maritagium: Glanvil</hi>'s Diſtinction is good; <hi>Maritagium</hi> eſt vel <hi>liberum</hi> vel <hi>ſervitio obnoxium:</hi> ſo that <hi>Maritagium</hi> the <hi>Genus,</hi> comprehends the Members, and both oppoſite one to another, as, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64437:15"/>
               <hi>free marriage,</hi> or not <hi>free marriage;</hi> let Sir <hi>Peter</hi> therefore anſwer this his own Argument as he thinks fit.</p>
            <p>As to what he pretends in the 22, 23, and 24 pages, I did not ſay that the Gift of <hi>Elleſmere</hi> to <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was but an Eſtate for Life, it being ſaid in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, to make Livery to be an Eſtate <hi>in maritagio,</hi> (though not <hi>in libero mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio</hi>) and to make Livery thereof would have been needleſs, if it had been a Gift in <hi>free marriage;</hi> Neither is <hi>Joane</hi> his Wife proved to be a Baſtard, ſo that that Precedent is out of doors; but I did give ſome Reaſons why that Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent would have ſtood him in no ſtead, if ſhe had been a Baſtard, and that a Gift in <hi>free marriage;</hi> and could yet ſay more in that particular, if occaſion did require: but that not being the Caſe, I will forbear to ſay any more concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>In his 24 page, and ſo on to the 42, (beſides ſome miſtakes of his, which, becauſe they are not material to the point, I will not here take notice of) he ſpends a great deal of time in proving, that <hi>Hellen</hi> the Wife of <hi>John Scot,</hi> was the Daughter of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> by his Wife
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64437:16"/>
               <hi>Joane</hi> Daughter of King <hi>John;</hi> whereas he did clearly prove the ſame, in his 28 and 29 pages, in very few words: and the ſame doth alſo appear by a Record hereafter mentioned, which very lately came to my knowledge; but yet for all that, this Precedent will do him no good, as well becauſe the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> is not proved to be a Baſtard, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehale</hi> were not given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin in libero ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio,</hi> as will anon appear; Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth indeed tell us, that thoſe Mannon were given <hi>in libero maritagio</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> but the Deed lately belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Somerfield Oldfeld</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> doth prove no ſuch thing, but doth only prove that the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> did miſtake himſelf, and think that they were given him <hi>in free marriage,</hi> when they were not ſo given; I therefore believing Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> that thoſe Mannors were given <hi>in free marriage</hi> to <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> when they were not; and perceiving <hi>Lhewellin</hi> to ſay that King <hi>John</hi> had given them to him, but not telling with whom, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as appears in the 13, 14, 15, and 16 pages of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda</hi>) if they were given to him <hi>in frank mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64437:16"/>with his Wife <hi>Joane</hi> the Daughter of the ſaid King, that the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> had not power to diſpoſe of them from his Son <hi>David,</hi> (who was his right Heir) could not find out any other way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile every thing in this particular, but by ſuppoſing that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> had a former Wife who was a Kinſwoman to King <hi>John,</hi> with whom thoſe Lands were given, and by whom he had his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Hellen:</hi> And what I ſaid was by way of conſequence, for I relied only upon my fourth Argument, as appears in the ſaid 13 page, and brought the other three but as concurrent; And what I there believed might very well have been true, for Sir <hi>Peter</hi> proves that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> had a former Wife; and if his words had been true in ſaying that thoſe Mannors were given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Joane in libero marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> my words muſt neceſſarily have been true alſo; for I was only miſtaken in <hi>Hellens</hi> Mother, by building upon that unſound foundation which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did there lay.</p>
            <p>But mark what work Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth make of it, now he hath proved <hi>Hellen</hi> to be <hi>Lhewellin</hi>'s Daughter by his ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64437:17"/>Wife <hi>Joane;</hi> for he in his 37 page grants all my Quotations, (I would I had cauſe to ſay the like by him) and alſo grants what by thoſe Lawyers is ſaid in the 14 and 15 pages of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Adden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> which is a certain ſign he doth not underſtand what they do ſay; for by what is there ſaid, it appears, that if a Man have Land given him <hi>in free mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> with a Wife, he hath only <hi>cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am cum uxore,</hi> and hath not ſo much as an Eſtate for his own life, until he be Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by the courteſie of <hi>England,</hi> and by conſequence he cannot diſpoſe of thoſe Lands to any perſon whatſoever from the next Heir; And this ignorance of his runs him upon his miſtake in the 36 and 37 pages of his latter Book, wherein he ſays, that a man would have but <hi>cuſtodiam cum uxore,</hi> although the Wife <hi>were not of the blood of the Donor:</hi> whereas you may ſee in the 14 and 15 pages of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> that though when Lands be given with a Woman to a Man <hi>in frank marriage,</hi> it is <hi>liberum tenementum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat niſi cuſtodiam cum uxore,</hi> yet it is (<hi>ſecus</hi>) otherways, when the Land is given in marriage, <hi>pro homagio
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64437:17"/>&amp; ſervitio viri,</hi> and one reaſon of this difference betwixt Land given <hi>in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> for which no ſervice is to be done, and Land given <hi>in marriage,</hi> for which <hi>Homage</hi> is to be done, is becauſe in the one Caſe, the Land may <hi>revert</hi> to the <hi>Donor,</hi> but in the other Caſe, the Land can never <hi>revert,</hi> as you may find in <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 7. cap. 18. who, after he hath told you what <hi>free marriage</hi> is, hath theſe words: <hi>Cum quis itaque ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram aliquam cum uxore ſua in maritagium ceperit, ſi ex eadem uxore ſua haeredem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit filium, vel filiam clamantem &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum infra quatuor parietes ſi idem vir uxorem ſuam ſupervixerit, ſive vixerit hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſive non, illi in vita ſua remanet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium illud, poſt mortem vero ipſius ad donatorem vel ejus haeredes eſt reverſurum. Sin autem ex uxore ſua nunquam habuerit haeredem, tunc ſtatim post mortem uxoris ad donatorem vel haeredes ejus revertetur maritagium. Et haec eſt quaedam cauſa quare de maritagio tali non ſolet recipi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magium. Si enim ſic donata eſſet terra aliqua in maritagium vel alio modo quod inde reciperetur homagium tune nunquam de cetero ad donatorem vel ejus haeredes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite poſſit reverti ut ſupradictum est.</hi> Sir
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64437:18"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> therefore muſt either confeſs that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> had no power to diſpoſe of thoſe Lands in ſuch manner as he did, and then that Precedent will be of no more force, (if the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> had been a Baſtard) than a Precedent would be of a Man who now ſhould give Lands <hi>is libero maritagio,</hi> to one who is not of the blood, or elſe he muſt acknowledge that thoſe Lands were given to <hi>Lhewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> but <hi>in maritagio,</hi> and ſo he being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do <hi>homage</hi> for them, might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of them as he did pleaſe; And that they were given to him but <hi>in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio,</hi> will appear, as well by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Livery of them (which is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in a Gift <hi>in frank marriage</hi>) as alſo by theſe following Records.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Clauſ. <hi>2.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> M. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>MAndatum est Vic: Warr: quod ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſeiſinam habere faciat <hi>Leoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> Principi Norwall: de Villa de <hi>Budiford</hi> cum pertinentiis ſuis quam Dominus <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes</hi> Rex Pater Domini <hi>Henrici</hi> Regis dedit ei <hi>in Maritagium</hi> cum <hi>Johanna</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore <hi>Henrici</hi> Regis uxore ipſius <hi>Leulini.</hi> Teſt.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Scilicet <hi>Willieſmo Mareſcallo</hi> Comite <hi>Pembrochis</hi> tune Rectore Regis &amp; Regni.</note> Comite apud <hi>Weſtm. 10.</hi> Oct.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64437:18"/>
               <bibl>Rot. Pip. de ann. <hi>2</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> Warr. &amp; Leic.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIllielmus</hi> de <hi>Cantilupo Philippus</hi> de <hi>Kinton</hi> pro eo reddit comp. de <hi>cxxviii. li. ii. s. bl.</hi> de firma de <hi>Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick:</hi> &amp; de quater viginti &amp; quinque li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris <hi>xvi. s. iiii. d. bl.</hi> de firma de <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtreſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>— Et <hi>Leuelino</hi> Principi Norwall: <hi>lxxvi s.</hi> in <hi>Budiford</hi> in <hi>maritagio</hi> cum <hi>Johanna</hi> uxore ſua, de dimidio anno <hi>per Breve Regis.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>But the Deed to <hi>John Scot</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> might be either <hi>in libero marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> according to the agreement of <hi>Lhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellin</hi> with <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> or elſe it might be <hi>in maritagio</hi> only, as it was given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin;</hi> ſo that be that Deed how it will, it will work nothing in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>In his 57, 58, and 59 pages, he ſeems much diſpleaſed with what I tell him in the 33 page of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda,</hi> concerning his partiality, and doth in ſome reſpects ſtrain my words further then he ſhould; But though I will not ſay any thing at this time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64437:19"/>this particular, for ſome reaſons I have formerly told him of, yet if he doth pleaſe to ſpeak of it to me at any time, when any judicious perſon is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I think I can make good what I ſaid, and that he will not be excuſed by that contradiction of his, when he ſays, page 58 and 59, that <hi>Admit he were partial never ſo much, in what I charge him with, yet he hopes what he hath written, I find it impartial to all, ſo far as he goes, or doth know.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his 60 and 61 pages, he tells me, that I go to excuſe an Error of mine, in calling <hi>Ralph Maniwaring Chief</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> becauſe I found in his <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Antiquities,</hi> page 160, and alſo in other places, there were in the time of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> ſometimes two Juſtices of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and ſometimes but one; But I did not abſolutly ſay, there were two Juſtices living both together in the time of the ſaid <hi>Ralph;</hi> I only did inſinuate, as you may ſee, in the 5 page of my <hi>Reply,</hi> and the 34 page of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> that it was poſſible there might be more than one at a time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was living I found ſome Deeds, directed <hi>Justiciariis,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64437:19"/>I am ſure the reaſons which he gives to the contrary in the 61 page of the firſt of his laſt two Books are very ſtrange ones; for he ſays that it is there to be underſtood of the Judges, &amp;c. <hi>ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively or with their Deputies under them;</hi> Now how can any Deed be directed to any Juſtice and his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> before he hath a ſucceſſor? or to their Deputies under them, if what he ſays in the ſame page be true, that <hi>then they executed their places themſelves, no power being given to them in thoſe ages to make or conſtitute a Deputy (by Commiſſion) at pleaſure, as we have now, and in theſe latter ages hath been uſually done?</hi> Neither doth he mend it afterwards, for he ſays, <hi>poſſibly upon an emergent occaſion, the Antient Earls might conſtitute another Judge for the preſent in the abſence of the other, to execute the place for a time, and ſo change them as oft as was thought good:</hi> Now if this conceit of his be true, that another Judge was conſtituted for a time, only in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the former, were there not then two Juſtices at one time? ſo that here are three very weak Anſwers given thereto; But I ſhall now make it further appear, that there was ſometimes a <hi>Chief
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64437:20"/>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in thoſe elder Ages, which I will thus prove.</p>
            <p>That the word <hi>Juſtitia</hi> (which then is of the Maſculine Gender according to that Rule, <hi>Maſcula nomina in</hi> a <hi>dicuntur multa virorum</hi>) was ſometimes in thoſe elder Ages uſed for the <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> I believe he cannot deny, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> page 144, I find a Deed thus directed; Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulphus <hi>Comes Ceſtriae, Conſtabulario ſuo, &amp; Dapifero,</hi> Juſtitice, <hi>&amp; Vicecomiti Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronibus &amp; Ballivis ſuis, ſalutem.</hi> I alſo in the 143 page of the ſaid Book, find this Deed following:
<q>
                  <hi>RAnulphus</hi> Dux <hi>Britanniae,</hi> &amp; Comes <hi>Ceſtriae</hi> &amp; <hi>Richmondiae,</hi> Omnibus tam praeſentibus quam futuris qui Chartam iſtam viderint &amp; audierint, Salutem. Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis quod ego dedi &amp; conceſſi <hi>Andreae</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio <hi>Mabiliae,</hi> &amp; Haeredibus ſuis, ut ſint libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri &amp; quieti de me &amp; meis Haeredibus de <hi>Teloneo</hi> per totam terram meam, &amp; in aqua, &amp; in terra, &amp; in Civitate <hi>Ceſtriae,</hi> &amp; extra, &amp; a Brevibus portandis, &amp; a Priſonibus capiendis &amp; cuſtodienis, &amp; a Namis capiendis, &amp; a Vigiliis faciendis nocte vel die, &amp; a caeteris hujuſmodi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinibus
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64437:20"/>&amp; exactionibus, nec de quere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâ aliquâ in Civitate <hi>Ceſtriae,</hi> vel extra, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeant in praeſentiâ meâ,
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>vel ſummi Juſtitiae mei:</hi> Et ſuper forisfacturam meam <hi>x Librarum</hi> prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, ne aliquis eos de ſupradictis libertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus impediat vel inquietet, ſed eas libere &amp; quiete teneant, Reddendo mihi &amp; Haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis annuatim <hi>vi</hi> Denarios ad Feſtum Sancti <hi>Michaelis.</hi> Hiis Teſtibus, <hi>Bertre</hi> Comitiſſa <hi>Ceſtriae, Radulfo</hi> de <hi>Meinewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, Radulfo</hi> Seneſchallo, <hi>Hugone</hi> de <hi>Boidele,</hi> &amp; <hi>Alano</hi> fratre ejus, <hi>Roaldo, Roberto</hi> Cam. <hi>Roberto Saraceno, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulfo Dubeldai, Nicolao</hi> filio <hi>Roberti, Thoma</hi> fratre ſuo, <hi>Willielmo Marmiun, Ricardo Poibel, Rogero</hi> Clerico, &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aliis. Apud <hi>Ceſtriam.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any perſon judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe words <hi>in praeſentia mea, vel</hi> Summi Juſtitiae <hi>mei,</hi> do not clearly prove, that there was a <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in thoſe elder Ages; for that Deed was made in the time of the ſaid <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> he being a witneſs to the ſame. And as I have proved in the fifth page of my <hi>Reply,</hi> that if there were then two <hi>Juſtices,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> was the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64437:21"/>Chief; ſo it will alſo eaſily appear, that the ſaid Deed was made, when the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> was Judge; for you may find in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 143, &amp; 144. that <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> did firſt write himſelf Duke of <hi>Britain</hi> in the year 1187, and did relinquiſh that Title in the year 1200. And you may ſee in the 172 page of the ſaid Book, that <hi>Philip</hi> de <hi>Orreby</hi> (who immediately ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi>) was not made Judge till about the year 1209.</p>
            <p>In the 62 and 63 pages, he thinks that he hath at laſt found out a fine device to cure what he formerly ſaid; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I told him (page 9. of my <hi>Reply</hi>) that I could not imagine how it was poſſible that the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton,</hi> to that, or any other Deeds of his own, could have his name either with the word <hi>Domino,</hi> or without, either five times for once, or at all, amongſt the Witneſſes ſubſcribed, unleſs he did fancy that he was a Witneſs to his own Deeds: He now pretends, that when he ſaid <hi>he had ſeen ſeveral other Deeds of the ſame perſon,</hi> he meant and underſtood, <hi>ſeveral other Deeds touching the ſame perſon: for the word</hi> (of) <hi>is uſed many times for</hi> concerning, <hi>as,</hi> of or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64437:21"/>concerning the ſame perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of his doth not at all make the matter better than it was before; for, as Men do not uſe to be Witneſſes to their own Deeds, ſo they did not uſe (and eſpecially in thoſe ages when the Deeds were ſo ſhort) to be Witneſſes to Deeds which concerned themſelves; And though he may poſſibly ſhew me a Deed made concerning a <hi>Geffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton,</hi> to which a <hi>Geffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton</hi> was a Witneſs, becauſe there were ſeveral <hi>Geffreys</hi> de <hi>Dutton</hi> living at that time; yet he muſt excuſe me, if I do not believe that he can ſhew me either ſeveral Deeds, or any one Deed in that age which doth concern a <hi>Geffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton,</hi> to which that <hi>Geffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton</hi> was a Witneſs, who was the Party concerned.</p>
            <p>In his 64 page he ſays, what he ſaid in his <hi>Addenda,</hi> p. 11. is not contrary to what he did write in the bottom of the fifth page of his <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia.</hi> Let the Reader therefore ſee how Sir <hi>Peter</hi> ſays in the 11 page of his <hi>Addenda,</hi> that, <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> was no Knight; <hi>For otherways he would have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf by his Title, as,</hi> Ego Galfridus
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64437:22"/>de Dutton Miles, <hi>or</hi> Ego
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Galfridus de Dutton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, <hi>&amp;c. which few Men will omit in their own Deeds, if they have really the honour of Knighthood.</hi> And let him alſo obſerve, how at the bottom of the fifth page of his ſaid <hi>Anſwer,</hi> ſpeaking of the word <hi>Domino,</hi> he ſays, <hi>that word is</hi> never <hi>uſed in old Deeds by the party himſelf, but where it is
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> joined with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other word, as,</hi> Ego Willielmus Manwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Dominus de Peover; and then let him judge whether thoſe expreſſions be contrary to each other, or not.</p>
            <p>In his 65 page he ſays, that I would fain palliate another groſs miſtake, in making <hi>Geffrey de Dutton</hi> the Father, to live on to be a Witneſs to the Deed of <hi>Geffrey de Dutton</hi> to his Daughter <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> of the Mannor of <hi>Nether Tabley;</hi> but if the Reader pleaſe to ſee the 36, 37, 38, and 39 pages of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> it will there appear to be very uncertain, whether it was any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake at all: And he himſelf after he hath ſaid all he can, doth confeſs in the 67 page of the firſt of his ſaid two Books, that his Deeds do but <hi>probably</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64437:22"/>demonſtrate, that <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was dead before; ſee therefore what a ſtir he keeps about nothing, for it is not material whether this be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake or not. And whereas he pretends page 68, that it is <hi>petitio principii</hi> to ſay, that the word <hi>Dominus</hi> doth always ſhew, that the perſon to whoſe name it is applied, was a Knight, or Clergyman; yet I have ſhewed that it is uſually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ſuch perſons, which is the only proof that can be had in this Caſe; and it lies upon him to prove, if he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict me therein, that it was ſo appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome one, who was neither Knight nor Clergyman; for of the higher No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility I do not ſpeak, to which kind of perſons the word <hi>Dominus,</hi> either as it ſignifies <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Sir,</hi> might ſometimes be applied: And though he ſays that thoſe very worthy perſons Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> and Mr. <hi>Blunt,</hi> are of opinion that the word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino</hi> was ſometimes alſo prefixed in thoſe elder ages to the names of perſons of better ſort and quality, though no Knights, as well as to Knights and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen, contrary to the opinion of ſome other skilful men, (as learned perſons do ſometimes differ from each other;)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64437:23"/>yet he doth not inſtance in any one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to make good what he ſays, and it will be a very hard matter ſo to do; for the proving that the word <hi>Dominus</hi> hath been prefixed to a perſons name, and ſometimes afterwards omitted, will not be ſufficient, becauſe I can prove that ſome who were certainly <hi>Knights,</hi> have been afterwards named without having the word <hi>Dominus</hi> prefixed, or the word <hi>Miles</hi> added to their names.</p>
            <p>In the 39 page of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> I told him of ſome words, which he pretended to have written, which I could not find in his Book; and for this in the 69 page of the firſt of his two Books, he ſays I would beſpatter him with a falſity therein, although in the 70 page, he confeſſes thoſe words were not in his <hi>Anſwer</hi> expreſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that it was a negligent error; and yet for all this, in the 64 and 65 pages of the firſt of his new Books, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that the words <hi>Ego Dominus</hi> A. B. <hi>dedi,</hi> &amp;c. (which were ſome of the words I could not find in his ſaid Book) were ſpoken of before, in the 7th page of his Book there mentioned, ſo that he commits the ſame Error again.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64437:23"/>
            <p>In the 68 page, he again takes notice how I had formerly ſaid, that <hi>Margaret</hi> was the Daughter and Heir of <hi>Geffrey Dutton,</hi> whereas he ſays ſhe was his Daughter, but not Heir, and this he calls a groſs miſtake of mine; but a groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake it cannot be, becauſe the ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> and her Heirs did enjoy ſeveral Mannors which were her Fathers, and becauſe it is not material to the point in hand, whether ſhe was or was not his Daughter and Heir. And whereas he is diſpleaſed at me for ſaying, <hi>if it was any miſtake at all,</hi> he muſt thank himſelf for that; for ſince he did ſo untruly quote the Book of <hi>Barlings,</hi> and ſo many other places, he muſt excuſe me, if I dare not rely too much upon his bare word.</p>
            <p>In his 67 page, he doth <hi>confeſs he calls one, Sir</hi> Geffrey Dutton <hi>of</hi> Chedil <hi>in his Book: but he calls him not Sir</hi> Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Dutton <hi>of</hi> Chedil <hi>Knight, as I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> whereas I cannot imagine what he ſhould be but Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> of <hi>Chedil</hi> Knight, being he was no Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, unleſs he would have him to be Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> or Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> Gentleman. And though he pretends,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64437:24"/>page 73. <hi>that Eſquires were none in thoſe ages,</hi> I ſhall refer the Reader for that to Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>'s <hi>Titles of Honour,</hi> pag. 830, 831, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though I confeſs the word <hi>Eſquire</hi> doth not often occur as a legal Addition, till after the Statute of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions made in the firſt year of King <hi>Henry</hi> V.</p>
            <p>From the end of the 73 page, to the end of the 84, inſtead of producing an Example where the word <hi>Dominus</hi> was applied to the name of a Layman, who was but an Eſquire or Gentleman, (which was the thing which he ought to have done) he vainly ſpends his time in acquainting you with ſome Notes of his, in Manuſcript, never yet printed, on the ſeveral Notions of the word <hi>Dominus,</hi> and the Engliſh word <hi>Sir;</hi> but as he hath there omitted ſome things to which thoſe words were uſed to be applied, ſo he went too far, when in his 77 and 79 pages, he applied to the Lady <hi>Hawiſe de Quency</hi> the word <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and the word <hi>Sir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his 86 page, and ſo on, to almoſt the end of the 89, he would fain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade the Reader, that <hi>Hugh Cyveliol</hi> was not One and twenty years of age
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64437:24"/>when he joined with his Mother <hi>Maude</hi> in giving <hi>Stivinghale</hi> to <hi>Walter Durdent</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and his Succeſſors, to which Deed <hi>Euſtace</hi> the Conſtable was a Witneſs, and tells you of a Precedent in his Book of <hi>Antiquities,</hi> pag. 114. &amp; 115. where you may find <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter joining with</hi> Ermentrude <hi>his Mother in the Grant of</hi> Wudemun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſlai <hi>to the Abby and Church of</hi> Abing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>in Barkſhire, Anno</hi> 6. Henrici 1. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Domini</hi> 1106. <hi>whiles he was ſcarce</hi> 12 <hi>years old, whereof the Book of</hi> Abington <hi>immediately before the Deed, ſaith thus,</hi> fol. 47. <hi>Ipſe Comes benefactum extulit, &amp; ſuo deſcripto roboravit: quod deſcriptum Sigillo quidem matris Signari conſtitit: nondum enim militari Baltheo cinctus, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno Sigillo literae quaelibet ab eo directae includebantur, hac de re; quod eò annotatur, Comitiſſae potiùs quam Comitis Sigillo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur.</hi> But he doth not give you the Deed in either of his two little Books, therefore I think fit to Tranſcribe it here, for the ſatisfaction of thoſe who have not ſeen the ſame, as I find it in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 114. but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed 122.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64437:25"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>RIcardus</hi> Ceſtrenſis Comes, &amp; Ermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudis Comitiſia mater ejus, Nigello de Oilii, &amp; Rogero filio Radulfi, &amp; omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Baronibus de Oxenford Scira, Salutem &amp; Amicitiam. <hi>Sciatis</hi> quia pro amore Dei &amp; anima Patris mei, &amp; remiſſion noſtrorum Peceatorum, Concedimus hidam illum, quam Droco de Andeleia dedit Ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Abbendonenſi, quae eſt in loco qui dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Wudemundeſlai:</hi> Nos eidem Ecsleſia concedimus &amp; auctorizamus perpetuò ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendam, ſolidam &amp; quietam ab omni no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro ſervitio: Et Rogerus filius Radulſi &amp; Succeſſores ejus ſint quieti in noſtro ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, quantum ad illam hidam pertinet: Et defendimus, ut nullo modo Rogerus, vel alius per eum, inquietet habitantes in terra illa: Hoo autem fecimus &amp; teſtimonio no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum Baronum; ſcilicet Willielmi filii Nigelli, &amp; Hugonis filii Normanni, &amp; Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardi Balaſte, &amp; Willielmi filii Auskitilli, &amp; Ricardi filii Nigelli, &amp; Domini Goisfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Capellani &amp; aliorum. Hoc actum eſt in ſexto Anno Regni Henrici Regis, in menſe Mail, in die Pentecoſtes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And to make the Reader believe that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> was not of age when he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64437:25"/>ſealed the ſaid Deed of <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> he tells you pag. 86. of his firſt Book, and pag. 30. of his latter Book, that what Earl <hi>Richard</hi> then did, was according to the Law and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of thoſe elder A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and <hi>that Earls and great Lords in thoſe former Ages did often join with their Mothers (who had the Tuition of them) in Deeds and Charters whiles they were very young, and before they attained the age of One and Twenty years;</hi> whereas I am confident Sir <hi>Peter</hi> cannot prove, that perſons who were under age, did then uſe to join with their Mothers, and ſo give away their Lands of Inheritance; for Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> in his <hi>Titles of Honour,</hi> pag. 785. at the bottom, and pag. 786. (the place which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> cites) tells us, <hi>that this of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, (<hi>viz.</hi> Earl <hi>Richard</hi>) <hi>is only a Note of a Monk after the Entry of the Charter of</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>and no part of the Body of the Charter; And in regard that he ſees no</hi> other Teſtimony of ancient time <hi>to ſecond it with the like, he ſhould think that the Monk was either groſly deceived in his reaſon of</hi> Nondum enim Militari Balteo cinctus eſt, <hi>or elſe that he meant only that the Earl was a Child within age, and that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64437:26"/>by reaſon of his Minority, Wardſhip, and the Tuition of his Mother (who joineth with him in the Charter) her Seal was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed to it, as alſo to his Letters;</hi> Alſo a little after, in the ſame page, Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> thus ſays, <hi>Now the Law being that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was Knighted, though before the age of One and Twenty, was of full age in regard of any Wardſhip, or any other Tuition (as preſently is further ſhewed) and the uſe being that ſuch great Lords were Knighted often, before they were of that age, and ſo had their full age ſupplied; and that perhaps alſo, while they were in ward, they uſed only their Guardians Seals, leſt the authority of a Seal of their own, before they had diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to uſe it, might have done them prejudice, in point of
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> honour at leaſt,</hi> if not in matter of profit. <hi>It is likely enough, that the Monk here took the phraſe of being</hi> not Knighted, <hi>to ſerve for being</hi> not of full age; <hi>So that the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of a Seal was not peculiar to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Knighthood, but to ſuch only (of what condition ſoever) as were of full age:</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth not in either of his two new Books give you the <hi>Charter</hi> of this Earl <hi>Richard</hi> and his Mother, but only tells you of it in general terms; for he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64437:26"/>cannot but ſee that it is not a ſelling or giving away any Land of Inheritance, but is only (according to Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>) <hi>a confirming</hi> of that Hyde of Land which <hi>Droco de Andeleia</hi> had given to <hi>Abington</hi> Church; And Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after in the next page ſays, <hi>though the wardſhip of the Body be ended (in the caſe of Knighting after the death of the Tenant by receiving the Order of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) yet
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> the Land continues to the Lords,</hi> until the full age of the Heir, <hi>as if he had not received the Order.</hi> What then is this to the Caſe of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> who did paſs away <hi>Stivinghale</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and his Succeſſors for ever? And without doubt the ſaid Land was given immediately after the death of Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> Father to the ſaid <hi>Hugh;</hi> for he dying Excommunicate, his friends in that age, would be very impatient un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he was abſolved; and it cannot be imagined that <hi>Maude</hi> did join with her ſon <hi>Hugh,</hi> becauſe he was under age; for that he could not be, becauſe he here paſſed away Lands for ever, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was old enough to take <hi>Melye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith</hi> Caſtle in the year 1142; and if he was then but 12 years of age, he would
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64437:27"/>be 23 years old in the year 1153, about which year his Father Earl <hi>Randle</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; his Mother therefore certainly had <hi>Stivinghale</hi> (which is not in <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> in his 86 page ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but is a Member of <hi>Coventry,</hi> as you may ſee in Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Antiquities of Warwickſhire,</hi> pag. 88, 128, 129. and in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 129.) as part of her Joynture, and thereupon joined with her Son; And indeed it had been a great ſhame to her, if her Son <hi>Hugh</hi> had been ſuch a tender Infant as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth ſuppoſe him to be, to make him part with thoſe Lands, upon that occaſion (if it could have been ſo done) and ſhe to part with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</p>
            <p>But though I doubt not but what is here ſaid, will give full ſatisfaction to all judicious perſons, yet I think fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Reader that I have a <hi>Pedigres</hi> by me, of the Barons <hi>de monte alto,</hi> drawn not long ſince by Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, and written all with his own hand, in which he makes the firſt <hi>Robert de Monte alto,</hi> Steward of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> (who, he ſays, lived in the time of King <hi>Steven</hi>) to have iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue (beſides other Sons who were youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64437:27"/>two Sons, <hi>Ralph</hi> and <hi>Robert,</hi> who were afterwards ſucceſſively Stewards of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> all which is certainly true.</p>
            <p>He alſo in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 131, doth give you this Deed of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> in which his Mother doth not join with him, which I think fit in this place to Tranſcribe.
<q>
                  <hi>HUgo</hi> Comes <hi>Ceſtriae,</hi> Conſtabulario ſuo, Dapifero, omnibus Baronibus ſuis, omnibus Hominibus ſuis, Francis &amp; Anglicis, tam futuris quam praeſentibus, Salutem. Concedo Sanctimonialibus de <hi>Bolintona</hi> Stagnum meum de <hi>Dunintona</hi> firmum terrae meae ſicut fuit tempore <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici</hi> Regis, in perpetuam Elemoſynam pro anima mea, &amp; Patris mei, &amp; meorum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teceſſorum: Et praecipio omnibus Homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis, quod habeant meam firmam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, ita quod nullus inde praedictis Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monialibus injuriam vel contumeliam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat. Teſte <hi>Roberto</hi> Dapifero de <hi>Monte alto, Filippo de Kima, Simone</hi> Filio <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berti, Willielmo Patric, Radulfo</hi> Filio <hi>Warneri, Rogero de Maletot,</hi> Johanne Priore de <hi>Trentham, Orm</hi> ejus Canonico, <hi>Rogero</hi> Monacho de <hi>Hambi, Willielmo</hi> Clerico Comitis qui Chartam ſcripſit apud <hi>Beltesford,</hi> &amp; multis aliis.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:64437:28"/>
            <p>Now that <hi>Robert de Montealto</hi> Stew ard of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> who was Witneſs to this Deed, was the firſt <hi>Robert de Montealto,</hi> will be manifeſt, becauſe the ſecond <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> came not to be <hi>Steward</hi> of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> during the life of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> as appean by the ſaid <hi>Pedigree,</hi> as alſo in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Book of <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 143. and in the 33 page of this Book, where you find <hi>Ralph</hi> the Steward, elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſecond <hi>Robert,</hi> outliving Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> and being a Witneſs to a Deed of <hi>Randle</hi> Son to the ſaid <hi>Hugh;</hi> it will therefore neceſſarily follow, if this Deed of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was made immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before the death of that <hi>Robert de Montealto,</hi> who was a Witneſs thereto, that the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was a great deal elder than his Wife <hi>Bertred;</hi> for though the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> did live ſomething lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth take notice of, yet I think it cannot be proved that he was living any conſiderable time after the ſaid <hi>Euſtace,</hi> and I know no reaſon why we ſhould conclude that <hi>Euſtace</hi> was ſlain immediately after he was a Witneſs to the other Deed, or that this <hi>Robert</hi> dyed preſently after he was a Witneſs to this Deed; nay, I think it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64437:28"/>will appear, that the aforeſaid Deed to the Nuns of <hi>Bolinton,</hi> was certainly made ſome years before the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> dyed, <hi>viz.</hi> in the time of King <hi>Stephen;</hi> for if it had been made when <hi>Henry</hi> the Second was King, Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would not have ſaid <hi>ſicut fuit tempore</hi> Henrici <hi>Regis,</hi> (as he there doth) but he would have ſaid, <hi>ſicut fuit tempore</hi> Henrici <hi>primi,</hi> or elſe he would have uſed ſome other words to diſtinguiſh King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt from the then King. Now King <hi>Stephen</hi> dying in the year 1154. and <hi>Bertred</hi> being not born till the year 1157. it will from this Deed be very clear, that if Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had ſealed the ſaid Deed immediately before King <hi>Stephen</hi> dyed, yet Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would be at the leaſt 24 years older than <hi>Bertred</hi> his Wife.</p>
            <p>And whereas he pretends that he ſhews, (pag. 93.) that Earl <hi>Hugh could neither be ſo old as I would now ſuppoſe him, nor yet that he was born Anno</hi> 1142. I anſwer thereto, that any man who can but count 20. (<hi>viz.</hi> how long it is from the year 1109. to the year 1129. or from the year 1110. to the year 1130.) if he looks on my <hi>Defence of</hi> Amicia, pag. 51. and my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 61, 62. may find that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64437:29"/>
               <hi>Hugh Cyvelick</hi> might be older than I ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I doubt Sir <hi>Peter</hi> is no good Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metician, as well becauſe of what he ſay here, as alſo becauſe he ſays in his <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 137. (which words you may alſo find before my <hi>Defence of Amicia,</hi> pag. 14.) <hi>that he was eight years older than his Wife, when he was married;</hi> whereas he is not now much above ſix years older, for as you may ſee in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 361. he was born the third of <hi>March,</hi> 1613. and his Lady was baptized the 23 day of <hi>May,</hi> 1620. And I believe Sir <hi>Peter</hi> will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge he reckons his own birth, not according to the <hi>Julian,</hi> but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the account of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and if he ſhould ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, he might be eaſily confuted: for as you may find in the ſaid 361 page, he had a ſiſter named <hi>Margaret,</hi> who was born <hi>September</hi> 29, 1612. and buried at <hi>Great Budworth, Octob.</hi> 12, 1612. ſo that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> could not be born the third day of <hi>March,</hi> 1613. according to the <hi>Julian</hi> account; for then his birth would have been but a little above five months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſaid ſiſter was born.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64437:29"/>
            <p>And whereas in the 49, 50, 51, 52 pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Addenda,</hi> I have proved out of the <hi>Welſh Hiſtory</hi> written by <hi>Caradocus Llanearuan,</hi> that <hi>Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok</hi> in all probability had another Wife before <hi>Bertred,</hi> becauſe he could be no leſs than 41 years of age when he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her, (although we ſuppoſe that he married her ſo ſoon as ſhe was 14 years old) Sir <hi>Peter</hi> to avoid this proof, doth endeavour all he can to diſparage Dr. <hi>Powell</hi> who did put out the ſaid <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and writ Notes thereon; but he was not ſo contemptible a perſon as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> would make him, for Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Antiquities</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> lib. 2. pag. 319. doth call the ſaid Doctor, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Antiquarum rimatorem induſtrium, atque Hiſtoriarum Britannicarum peritiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum:</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth alſo very well know that it is not the Doctor, but <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radocus Llancaruan</hi> which I do cite; he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will not ſuffer the ſaid Book to be read as it ſhould have been printed, but would have it read according as he doth pleaſe; which liberty if he may take, he hath very ill fortune, if he cannot keep it from ſaying any thing contrary to his own mind; then he will read it, not as it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64437:30"/>ought to have been printed, but as it is miſprinted, and thinks he ſhews a great deal of skill, in proving that it cannot be true as it is miſprinted, which every one will confeſs as well as himſelf. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although in his <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquitles</hi> in the Fifth Chapter, concerning the Kings of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Princes of <hi>Wales,</hi> in which Chapter he did quote <hi>Ingulphus, Orderiews, Cambden, Matthew Paris,</hi> and others, and did tell you there in his 44 page, that in theſe <hi>Welſh</hi> matters, he did chiefly <hi>follow the Welſh Hiſtory put out by Dr.</hi> Powell, 1584. yet now he will alſo diſparage the ſaid <hi>Hiſtory</hi> all that he can.</p>
            <p>But that he may ſeem to have ſome reaſon for what he ſays, he will tell you, that in that very place where <hi>Caradocus</hi> ſpeaks of taking <hi>Melyenith,</hi> he alſo ſays, that at that time King <hi>Steven</hi> took <hi>Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Mandevile</hi> Priſoner at St. <hi>Albons,</hi> whereas <hi>Mat: Paris</hi> ſub anno 1142. ſays, it was <hi>William Mandevile</hi> who was there taken, and therefore he will not have <hi>Caradocus</hi> to be believed in other things; but this which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> here ſays will be of no force, firſt, becauſe though <hi>Mat: Paris</hi> be a very good Author, yet <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docus</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:64437:30"/>(if there was nothing elſe in the Caſe) ought to be believed before the ſaid <hi>Mat: Paris,</hi> becauſe the ſaid <hi>Carado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> was living when the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> did win <hi>Melyenith,</hi> and when the ſaid <hi>Geffrey de Mandevile</hi> was taken Priſoner, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſaid <hi>Mat: Paris</hi> lived a long time afterwards, for he dyed in the year 1259. which was 117 years after that time; ſecondly, becauſe what <hi>Carodocus</hi> ſays concerning the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> in his ſaid 197 page, is very true, whoſe words are theſe:
<q>AT that time, <hi>(viz. 1142.)</hi> King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> took <hi>Geffrey Mandevile</hi> Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at St. <hi>Albon,</hi> where the Earl of <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> was like to be drowned by default of his Horſe; The Earl <hi>Mandevile</hi> gave to the King for his liberty, the Tower of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> with the Caſtles of <hi>Walden</hi> and <hi>Plaſſey,</hi> who afterward lived by ſpoil of Abbeys, and was ſlain in a skirmiſh againſt the King.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now that <hi>Caradocus</hi> doth not miſtake herein, will thus appear, If you look in <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Huntington,</hi> (who lived in the time of the ſaid King <hi>Stephen</hi>) pag. 393. line 15. you may thus read:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64437:31"/>
               <q>EOdem anno cepit Rex <hi>Gaufridum de Magnavilla</hi> in Curia ſua apud ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum <hi>Albanum</hi> magis ſecundum retributio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem nequitiae conſulis, quam ſecundum j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> gentium, magis ex neceſſitate quam ex ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtate; Niſi enim hoc egiſſet, perfidia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulis illius regno privatus fuiſſet; Igitur ut Rex eum liberaret, reddidit ei Turrim Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doniae &amp; Caſtellum de <hi>Waledene</hi> &amp; illud de <hi>Plaiſſeiz,</hi> poſſeſſionibus igitur caren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſul praedictus invaſit Abbatiam <hi>Ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſem</hi> &amp; Monachis expulſis raptores im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit, &amp; Eccleſiam Dei ſpeluncam fecit la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronum.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo if you peruſe the Hiſtory of <hi>Simeon Dunelmenſis</hi> (who lived in the time of the ſaid King <hi>Steven,</hi> and whoſe Hiſtory was continued for about 25 years by <hi>John</hi> Prior of <hi>Hagulſted</hi>) col. 273. line 15. you may thus read: <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridus enim de</hi> Magnavilla <hi>ejectis Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis Monaſterio de</hi> Ramesbi <hi>abuſus est vice Caſtri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Roger Hoveden</hi> (who lived in the times of King <hi>Henry</hi> 2. <hi>R.</hi> 1. and King <hi>John,</hi> in his Annals printed at <hi>Franfurt,</hi> 1601. pag. 488. l. 41.) thus ſays:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64437:31"/>
               <q>ANno autem ipſo conſul <hi>Gaufridus de Mandevilla</hi> Regem validiſſime vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avit, &amp; in omnibus valde glorioſus efful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit; Menſe autem Auguſti miraculum juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia ſua dignum virtus divina monſtravit; Duos namque qui monachis evulſis Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Dei converterant in Caſtella, ſimiliter peecantes ſimili poena mulctavit; <hi>Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> namque <hi>Marmiun</hi> vir bellicoſus hoc in Eccleſia de <hi>Coventree</hi> perverſus exegerat; Porro <hi>Gaufridus</hi> ut diximus in Eccleſia <hi>Rameſienſi</hi> ſcelus idem patraverat.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And a little before in the ſaid page, he alſo tells how the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner at St. <hi>Albon,</hi> and delivered the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and the Caſtles of <hi>Wallinden</hi> and <hi>Plaſſeis</hi> to the then King.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Gulielmus Nubrigenſis</hi> (who lived in the times of <hi>R.</hi> 1. and King <hi>John</hi>) thus writes, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap. xi.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>EOdem tempore Rex <hi>Stephanus</hi> cepit <hi>Gaufridum de Magnavilla</hi> in curia ſua apud <hi>Sanctum Albanum:</hi> non quidem honeſte &amp; ſecundum jus pro merito ejus: &amp; metu ſcilicet, quod expediret, quam quod
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64437:32"/>deceret plus attendens. Erat enim idem <hi>Gaufridus</hi> homo Audaciſſimus, &amp; magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum virium, ſimul &amp; Artium: praeclaram illam Arcem <hi>Lundonienſem</hi> cum duabus aliis Munitionibus non ignobilibus poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, &amp; ſubtili aſtutia ingentia moliens.</q>
            <p>And afterwards in the ſame Chapter he ſpeaks how the King did wreſt from the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> with his two other Caſtles, and alſo what the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> did to the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Rameſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Raph de Diceto,</hi> who was Dean of <hi>Pauls</hi> in King <hi>John</hi>'s time, in his <hi>Abbrev: Chronic:</hi> col. 508. line 32. thus ſays:
<q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1142.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>STephanus</hi> Rex <hi>Gaufridum</hi> de <hi>Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villa</hi> cepit in Curia ſua, qui ut libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, reddidit turrim <hi>Lundoniae</hi> &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtella ſua.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Gervaſius</hi> a Benedictine Monk of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (who lived in the time of King <hi>John,</hi> col. 1360. line 7.) thus writes: M CX LIIII.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64437:32"/>
               <q>REx <hi>Stephanus</hi> cepit Comitem <hi>Gaufri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> de <hi>Mandavilla</hi> in Curia ſua apud ſanctum <hi>Albanum,</hi> magis ex neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, quam ex honeſtate, Niſi enim hoc fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſet, ut a pluribus dicebatur, perfidia Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis regno privandus eſſet. Captus itaque Comes nulla potuit occaſione liberari, niſi ſua Caſtella reſignans Regiae pareret volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati. Reddidit ergo Turrim <hi>Londoniae</hi> &amp; Caſtellum de <hi>Waldene</hi> &amp; illud de Pleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiz &amp; liberatus eſt. Comes igitur muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus carens, &amp; a Militari crudelitate ſe cohibere non valens; invaſit abbatiam de <hi>Rameſeia,</hi> &amp; de Eccleſia Dei non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ritus Juſtitiam, ſpeluncam fecit Latronum.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>John Brompton</hi> col. 1033. l. 1.
<q>EOdem anno Comes <hi>Galfridus</hi> de <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davilla</hi> a Rege captus pro reſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne turris <hi>Londonienſis</hi> &amp; Caſtelli de <hi>Walde</hi> poſtea liberatur, qui poſſeſſionibus carens, cum adhuc magnam haberet fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam confeſtim abbathiam <hi>Sancti Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti</hi> de <hi>Rameſeye</hi> invaſit &amp; Monachis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſis raptores immiſit, &amp; ſanctum Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium ſpeluncam fecit latronum.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64437:33"/>
            <p>But I ſhall, after all this, ſhew you what <hi>Mat: Paris</hi> himſelf ſays in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition put out by Dr. <hi>Wats,</hi> pag. 79. which is the ſame place which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth cite, whoſe words are theſe:
<q>EOdem tempore Rex <hi>Stephanus</hi> cepit <hi>Willielmum</hi> de <hi>Mandevilla</hi> apud Sanctum <hi>Albanum</hi> unde reddidit Regi Turrim <hi>Londoniarum</hi> cum Caſtellis de <hi>Waldene</hi> &amp; de <hi>Pleſſiz</hi> antequam a vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſolveretur. Qui carens poſſeſſionibus paternis, invaſit abbatiam <hi>Ramefienſem,</hi> atque Monachis expulſis raptores immiſit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But on the other ſide of the Leaf, <hi>viz. pag.</hi> 80. <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 17. in the year 1143. he thus ſays:
<q>EOdem anno <hi>Robertus Marmimi</hi> vit bellicoſus qui Monachos <hi>Coventren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> a ſuo Monaſterio expulerat, &amp; de Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia illa Caſtellum fecerat, dum contra ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes decertaret, inter praedones ſuos, ante ipſum Monaſterium, ſolus peremptus eſt, &amp; excommunicatus morte depaſcitur ſempi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna.
<note n="*" place="margin">Noto.</note> Eodem vero tempore <hi>Gaufridus</hi> Conſul de <hi>Mandavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> qui idem ſcelus patraverat in Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64437:33"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>Rameſienſi</hi> ante ipſam Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am inter Conſortes ſuorum acies, a pedite quodam viliſſimo ſolus ſagitta per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſus, occubuit interfectus, <hi>&amp;c. So that the Reader may plainly ſee, how deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Sir</hi> Peter <hi>doth here deal; for find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in</hi> Mat: Paris <hi>called</hi> William de Mandevile <hi>on one ſide of the Leaf, (through either the ſlip of</hi> Mat: Paris<hi>'s Pen, or the Printer's negligence) he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints the Reader with that, but never tells him how he is on the other ſide of the Leaf called</hi> Geffrey de Mandevile. <hi>And that this was purpoſely done, may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, becauſe if</hi> Mat: Paris <hi>had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him</hi> William <hi>on both ſides of the Leaf, yet</hi> Caradocus, <hi>who was then liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having called him</hi> Geffrey, <hi>Sir</hi> Peter <hi>ſhould have conſulted other Authors, to have ſeen which of them two had been in the right; but theſe ancient Authors being againſt him, it was a good way to let them alone.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore leave it to the Reader to judge, whether <hi>Caradocus Llancaruan</hi> be not to be believed concerning <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>'s taking of <hi>Melyenith,</hi> being the ſame was taken when he was living; as alſo whether it doth not certainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64437:34"/>by that proof, that <hi>Hugh Cyvelio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was at the leaſt 41 years old when he married <hi>Bertred,</hi> and by conſequence in all probability imaginable had a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wife, for which reaſon, (if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofs were laid aſide) there is no juſt cauſe to ſuſpect <hi>Amicia</hi> to be illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and with this I will conclude my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his former Book.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Latin</hi> Epiſtle to the Judges, (which I ſuppoſe to be Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s, though he doth not vouchſafe to ſet his name thereto) he ſaid I was the firſt Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of this Controverſie; but whether that be ſo or not, let the Reader judge by what I have ſaid in my Epiſtle before my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia,</hi> and in the ſecond and third pages of my <hi>Reply.</hi> Alſo in the ſame Epiſtle, when he doth appeal to the Judges, he doth not put the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether the Law was different in the time of <hi>Glanvil</hi> in this point of <hi>free marriage</hi> from what it is now? But he propoſeth this Queſtion, Whether or no in the time of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> by our ancient Law, it was lawful for any Man to give Land in <hi>free marriage</hi> with his Baſtard Daughter, although the Law being now changed, the Law doth not at this day
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64437:34"/>permit a Gift in <hi>frank marriage</hi> with a Baſtard Daughter? By which he proves himſelf to be very like the Gentleman he ſpeaks of in the 14 pages of both his Books, <hi>who would needs diſpute about a</hi> Croſs, <hi>and the queſtion must be — Whether the Croſs was a Croſs or no Croſs?</hi> For if the Law be now clearly and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly changed in this particular point of <hi>frank marriage,</hi> from what it was in the days of <hi>Glanvil</hi> (as he in his Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion abſolutely ſays it is) it is then as certain, that Lands might have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>free marriage</hi> to thoſe not of the blood in the time of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> as it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that a Croſs is a Croſs; (but this Point muſt be otherwayes proved than by ſuch a frivolous queſtion as this is.)</p>
            <p>He alſo in the ſame Epiſtle, tells thoſe Reverend Judges, how highly he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Divinity before other Studies; but if he had been ſo converſant therein, as he would have them to believe, it ſeems ſtrange to me, that he hath not better learnt his duty to his deceaſed Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother; for we are bound to honour all our Parents, whether mediate or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate; and whether they be living, or dead: And I believe he will not find
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64437:35"/>any Precedent in Scripture, where any one did divulge the ſhame of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, out of whoſe loyns he did deſcend except that of wicked <hi>Ham,</hi> which pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern is in ſome reſpects exceeded by Sir <hi>Peter;</hi> for <hi>Ham</hi> did really find his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naked: and when the other Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> had co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ered their Father with a Garment, he did not offer to reveal his Fathers nakedneſs again and again.</p>
            <p>As for his ſecond Book, which he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> it ſo falls out, that there is nothing therein, but what is in his former Books, and is already anſwer'd; though if there had, I ſhould not have preſumed to have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven any Anſwer thereto; becauſe thoſe learned perſons know well enough what the Law was, and is in all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and cannot receive any information therein, either from Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> or me, or be deceived by his miſrecitals in his ſaid Books; However, I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how ſlightly he ſpeaks of the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in his 48 page, and alſo how he hath ſuch light expreſſions in his Book directed to the Judges, as I believe were never uſed before by any perſon of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, to ſuch Reverend and Learned Men. No wonder therefore, if he ſpeak
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64437:35"/>courſely of me, and tell me of ſo many Impertinencies; but whether I be guilty of them, or of thoſe untruths, or of that opprobrious language, which he doth charge me with, let the indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be Judge. And whereas it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he is reſolved to have the laſt word, although he have nothing new to ſay; and that his Writing again be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary both to his duty to his deceaſed Grandmother, and to his promiſe in Print: I do therefore declare, If what Sir <hi>Peter</hi> writes hereafter be no more to the purpoſe, than that is which he hath ſaid in his two (laſt) Books, that I will not appear in Print againſt him any more, but will chooſe to vindicate my Grandmother and my ſelf by word of mouth, whenſoever I ſhall have any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſo to do; only let me now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the judicious Reader, that ſome other Judges have declared their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the <hi>Legitimacy of</hi> Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, beſides thoſe three who formerly did ſo, and who were ſpoken of by Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> in the 49 page of the latter of his laſt Books.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Baddeley,</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. 15. 1674/5.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
